<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id jjournal-id-type="publisher">GRC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Gosudarstvo, religiia, tserkov' v Rossii i za rubezhom </journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta" />
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub" />
      <issn pub-type="epub" />
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript" />
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article_type">
          <subject>Research Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="subject_areas">
          <subject> </subject>
      </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Orthodox Theology and the Temptation of Power</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running" />
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Namli</surname>
            <given-names>Elena</given-names>
          </name>
          <email />
          <role content-type="1" />
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1" />
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <institution />
          <addr-line content-type="addrline1" />
          <addr-line content-type="city" />
          <addr-line content-type="state" />
          <addr-line content-type="zipcode" />
          <addr-line content-type="country" />
      </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" />
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
      <elocation-id />
      <history>
        <date data-type="received">
          <day />
          <month />
          <year>2014</year>
      </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement />
        <copyright-year />
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <b>The growing political and social role of the Russian Orthodox Church is one of the most challenging issues raised by recent developments in Russia. What do these developments represent? This article offers a critical analysis of the Russian Orthodox Church’s involvement in Russian politics. Offering a theological perspective, the paper shows that the Russian Orthodox Church fails to make proper use of its own theological tools when it chooses to act as a partner of the state, rather than as an independent political agent. One of the most devastating consequences of this choice is that the Church provides a symbolic legitimation of widespread and growing nationalism. The analysis is focused upon the social doctrine of the Church and the official publications on the human rights. The texts of these documents are then related to some alternative theological positions within the Russian Orthodox tradition. It is argued that this tradition possesses theological resources to enrich the political life with constructive contribution, while eschewing the rhetoric of cultural exclusivism and nationalism.</b>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>social ethics</kwd>
        <kwd>moral theology</kwd>
        <kwd>Russian Orthodox Church and politics</kwd>
        <kwd>public reason</kwd>
        <kwd>church and state.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="0" />
        <page-count count="0" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
