<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id jjournal-id-type="publisher">GRC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Gosudarstvo, religiia, tserkov' v Rossii i za rubezhom </journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta" />
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub" />
      <issn pub-type="epub" />
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">GRC-0000-0000-000</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article_type">
          <subject>Research Letter ???</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="subject_areas">
          <subject> </subject>
      </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Bioethical Issues of In Vitro Fertilization in Russian Orthodox Debates</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running" />
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tarabrin</surname>
            <given-names>Roman</given-names>
          </name>
          <email />
          <role content-type="1" />
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1" />
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <institution />
          <addr-line content-type="addrline1" />
          <addr-line content-type="city" />
          <addr-line content-type="state" />
          <addr-line content-type="zipcode" />
          <addr-line content-type="country" />
      </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" />
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
      <elocation-id>GRC-0000-0000-000</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date data-type="received">
          <day />
          <month />
          <year>2021</year>
      </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement />
        <copyright-year />
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <b>An increasing number of Orthodox Christians are turning to methods of assisted reproduction. However, the ambivalent position of the “Basis of the Social Concept of the Russian Orthodox Church” (2000) does not give believers clear ethical guidelines as to which reproductive methods are acceptable. In addition, the one-sided interpretation of the “Basis” led to a complete rejection of in vitro fertilization (IVF). The Church's commission “Intercouncil Presence” has developed a draft document that aims to clarify the ambiguous position of the “Basis” regarding reproductive technologies. In February 2021, the draft document, “Ethical issues related to in vitro fertilization,” was published on the Church’s official website. This paper analyzes the discussions that took place both before and after the publication. The author shows that IVF opponents do not understand the problem under discussion, using irrelevant, selective data that do not reflect the real state of medical practice to confirm their arguments. Analyzing the objections, the author shows that the death of embryos during IVF occurs due to natural causes, and therefore cannot be equated with murder. It is also argued that the level of congenital pathology in children remains at the level of a fraction of a percent and therefore cannot make IVF ethically unacceptable. Also, the article challenges concerns about the harm that IVF causes to pregnant women. Besides, the article reflects publications showing the possibility of the practical application of the published draft document.</b>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>bioethics</kwd>
        <kwd>reproductive technologies</kwd>
        <kwd>in vitro fertilization</kwd>
        <kwd>infertility</kwd>
        <kwd>Russian Orthodox Church</kwd>
        <kwd>Inter-council Presence.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="0" />
        <page-count count="0" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
