<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id jjournal-id-type="publisher">GRC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Gosudarstvo, religiia, tserkov' v Rossii i za rubezhom </journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta" />
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub" />
      <issn pub-type="epub" />
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript" />
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article_type">
          <subject>Research Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="subject_areas">
          <subject> </subject>
      </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Problem of Theological Languages in “The Big Trilogy” by Fr. Sergius Bulgakov</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running" />
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Khondzinsky</surname>
            <given-names>Pavel</given-names>
          </name>
          <email />
          <role content-type="1" />
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1" />
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <institution />
          <addr-line content-type="addrline1" />
          <addr-line content-type="city" />
          <addr-line content-type="state" />
          <addr-line content-type="zipcode" />
          <addr-line content-type="country" />
      </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" />
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
      <elocation-id />
      <history>
        <date data-type="received">
          <day />
          <month />
          <year>2020</year>
      </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement />
        <copyright-year />
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <b>Since Christian theology, in order to formulate the articles of faith, inevitably uses the categorical apparatus of historically established philosophical traditions, the problem of theological languages is objectively present. This problem is primarily connected with the revealing of a correct correlation between those languages, which is required for maintaining the unity of the Holy Tradition. The issue in question had obtained a special significance for the Russian theological tradition of the 19th and 20th centuries, due to a fundamental paradigm shift in philosophy in the modern era and under the rapid development of Russian religious philosophy. Father Sergius Bulgakov, in particular intended to illustrate that the basic Christian dogmas, which still had not had an adequate exposition, could only be explained in the “ language of Sophiology”. The present article analyzes the critique of the historical languages of theology, which was presented by Fr. Sergius in his so-called “The big trilogy” that includes his last three large works (“The Lamb of God”, “The Comforter”, “Bride of the Lamb”), it also reveals the peculiarities of the sophiological language of his own. Finally, based on the undertaken analysis, the article suggests a conceptual characterization of the “language of Sophiology”, as well as a conclusion about the association between Fr. Sergius’ theological intentions and Russian “New Theology” of the early 20th century.</b>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Fr. Sergius Bulgakov</kwd>
        <kwd>Sophiology</kwd>
        <kwd>triadology</kwd>
        <kwd>“New Theology”</kwd>
        <kwd>the Russian theological tradition.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="0" />
        <page-count count="0" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
