<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id jjournal-id-type="publisher">GRC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Gosudarstvo, religiia, tserkov' v Rossii i za rubezhom </journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta" />
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub" />
      <issn pub-type="epub" />
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript" />
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article_type">
          <subject>Research Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="subject_areas">
          <subject> </subject>
      </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>«A Place Where God Has Touched the Land in a Special Way»: Medjugorje as an International and Intercultural Space</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running" />
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Belaj</surname>
            <given-names>Marijana</given-names>
          </name>
          <email />
          <role content-type="1" />
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1" />
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <institution />
          <addr-line content-type="addrline1" />
          <addr-line content-type="city" />
          <addr-line content-type="state" />
          <addr-line content-type="zipcode" />
          <addr-line content-type="country" />
      </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" />
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
      <elocation-id />
      <history>
        <date data-type="received">
          <day />
          <month />
          <year>2014</year>
      </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement />
        <copyright-year />
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <b>After the work by the Dutch anthropologist Mart Bax, Medjugorje gained an academic reputation of a showcase for a pilgrimage space with religious, ethnic and political conflicts. From the very beginning of its pilgrimage history, Medjugorje as a sacred place attracted believers of various religious affiliations. The intention of this paper is to open up a different perspective in contrast to one proposed by Bax, namely, a perspective of international and intercultural communication through the shaping of Medjugorje pilgrimage. By analyzing primarily narrative expressions, but also embodied experiences and material objects, the paper sketches situations and manifestations of such interaction and communication. At the same time, it points to the obstacles in the processes that have emerged from the construction and interpretation of cultural differences. The paper concludes with an attempt to show that Medjugorje may be seen as an example of interculturality, unless religion and identity are not approached as something given or as a kind of a ghetto.</b>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Medjugorje</kwd>
        <kwd>Balkans</kwd>
        <kwd>pilgrimage</kwd>
        <kwd>internationality</kwd>
        <kwd>interculturality.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="0" />
        <page-count count="0" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
