<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id jjournal-id-type="publisher">GRC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Gosudarstvo, religiia, tserkov' v Rossii i za rubezhom </journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta" />
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub" />
      <issn pub-type="epub" />
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript" />
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article_type">
          <subject>Research Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="subject_areas">
          <subject> </subject>
      </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Philosophical Rationality between Religion and Science: Russian Hegelianism at the End of the 19th Century</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running" />
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Antonov</surname>
            <given-names>Konstantin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email />
          <role content-type="1" />
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1" />
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">
          <institution />
          <addr-line content-type="addrline1" />
          <addr-line content-type="city" />
          <addr-line content-type="state" />
          <addr-line content-type="zipcode" />
          <addr-line content-type="country" />
      </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub" />
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
      <elocation-id />
      <history>
        <date data-type="received">
          <day />
          <month />
          <year>2015</year>
      </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement />
        <copyright-year />
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <b>The article analyzes the “religion and science” problem as mapped out by two representatives of Russian Hegelianism in the end of the nineteenth century - Boris Chicherin and Pavel Bakunin. The analysis of relations between science and religion allowed both thinkers to articulate the most general grounds of their philosophical systems. The article outlines a number of important common features in interpretations and conclusions of both philosophers. For both, the struggle between “scientific” and “religious” worldviews seems to be a confrontation of the two forms of false consciousness. For both, philosophical rationality is the supreme arbiter in the conflict of religion and science. They outline a project of philosophical theology according to which God reveals Himself not in religious feeling but in reason, in the depth of self-consciousness. Overall, both thinkers give a solution typical for Russian metaphysics: by opposing both scientific and religious obscurantism, they hope for philosophical mediation in the case of reestablishing of balance of divergent spheres of cultural and spiritual life.</b>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>religion</kwd>
        <kwd>science</kwd>
        <kwd>philosophical theology</kwd>
        <kwd>Russian religious philosophy</kwd>
        <kwd>Hegelianism</kwd>
        <kwd>B. Chicherin</kwd>
        <kwd>P. Bakunin</kwd>
        <kwd>religious consciousness.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="0" />
        <page-count count="0" />
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
